Wonder by R.J. Palacio.
Part four.
Jack.
Now here is my secret. It is very simple. It is only with one's heart that
one can see clearly. What is essential is invisible to the eye.
Antoine de Saint-Exupéry, The Little Prince.
The call.
SO IN AUGUST, my parents got this call from Mr.. Tushman,, the middle school
director.. And my Mom said:, "“Maybe he calls all the new kids to
welcome them,”." and my dad said:, "“That’s a lot of kids he’d be calling.”."
So my mom called him back,, and I could hear her talking to Mr.. Tushman on the phone..
This is exactly what she said:.
"“Oh,, hi, Mr.. Tushman.. This is Amanda Will, returning your call?."
Pause.
"Oh,, thank you!. That’s so nice of you to say.."
"He is looking forward to it.." Pause.
"Yes.." Pause. "Yeah.." Pause. "Oh., Sure.."
Long pause. "Oh, Uh-huh.." Pause. "Well,, that’s so nice of you to say.."
Pause. "Sure." "Oh, Wow. Oh."
Super long pause.
"I see,. of course.. I’m sure he will.. Let me write it down."
"got it.." "I’ll call you after I’ve had a chance to talk to him,, okay??"
Pause.
"No,, thank you for thinking of him."
"Bye-bye."
And when she hung up,, I was like,, "“what’s up,? what did he say?”?"
And Mom said:, "“Well,, it’s actually very flattering, but kind of sad,, too..
See,, there’s this boy who’s starting middle school this year,, and he’s never
been in a real school environment before because he was homeschooled,. so Mr..
Tushman talked to some of the lower school teachers to find out who they
thought were some of the really,, really great kids coming into fifth grade,.
and the teachers must have told him you were an especially nice kid—, —which I
already knew,, of course—. —and so, Mr..
Tushman is wondering if he could count on you to sort of shepherd this new boy
around a bit?”.
“Like, let him hang out with me?”? I said..
“Exactly,”, said Mom.. “He called it being a ‘welcome buddy.’”.
“But, why me?”?
“I told you.. Your teachers told Mr..
Tushman that you were the kind of kid who’s known for being a good egg.. I
mean,, I’m so proud that they think so highly of you..
“Why is it sad?”?
“What do you mean?”?
“You said it’s flattering, but kind of sad,, too.”.
“Oh.”, Mom nodded.. “Well,, apparently this boy has some sort of um,
I guess there’s something wrong with his face or something like that.. Not sure..
Maybe he was in an accident..
Mr.. Tushman said he’d explain a bit more when you come to the school next week.”.
“School doesn’t start until September!”.
“He wants you to meet this kid before school starts.”.
“Do I have to?”?
Mom looked a bit surprised..
“Well,, no,, of course not,”, she said,.
“but, it would be the nice thing to do,, Jack.”.
“If I don’t have to do it,”, I said,, “I don’t want to do it.”.
“Can you at least think about it?”? “I’m thinking about it, and I don’t want to
do it.”. “Well,, I’m not going to force you,”, she said,. “but, at least think about it
some more,, okay?? I’m not calling Mr..
Tushman back until tomorrow,, so just sit with it a bit.. I mean,, Jack,, I really
don’t think it’s that much to ask that you spend a little extra time with some
new kid..
“It’s not just that he’s a new kid,, Mom,”, I answered..
“He’s deformed.”.
“That’s a terrible thing to say,, Jack.”."
"“He is,, Mom.”."
"“You don’t even know who it is!”."
"“Yeah,, I do,”." I said,.
because I knew the second she started talking about him, that it was that kid named August.
Carvel I REMEMBER SEEING him for the first time in front of the Carvel on Amersfort
Avenue when I was about 5 or 6.
Me and Veronica,, my babysitter,, were sitting on the bench outside the store
with Jamie,, my baby brother,, who was sitting in his stroller facing us..
I guess I was busy eating my ice cream cone, because I didn’t even notice the
people who sat down next to us.
And at one point, I turned my head to suck the ice cream out of the bottom of
my cone,. and that’s when I saw him:.
August..
He was sitting right next to me..
I knew it wasn’t cool,, but I kind of went, "Ooh." when I saw him because I
honestly got scared.. I thought he was wearing a zombie mask or something.. It
was the kind of "Ooh." you say when you’re watching a scary movie and the
bad guy like jumps out of the bushes..
Anyway,, I know it wasn’t nice of me to
do that,. and though the kid didn’t hear me,, I know his sister did..
"“Jack!, We have to go!”." said Veronica..
She had gotten up and was turning the stroller around because Jamie,, who had
obviously just noticed the kid,, too,, was about to say something embarrassing.. So,
I jumped up kind of suddenly,, like a bee had landed on me,, and followed Veronica
as she zoomed away..
I could hear the kid’s mom saying softly behind us:.
"“Okay,, guys,. I think it’s time to go,”."
and I turned around to look at them one more time.. The kid was licking his ice
cream cone,. the mom was picking up his scooter,. and the sister was glaring at
me like she was going to kill me..
I looked away quickly..
"“Veronica,, what is wrong with that kid?”?"
I whispered.. "“Hush,, boy!”." she said,, her voice angry..
I loved Veronica,, but when she got mad,, she got mad. Meanwhile,, Jamie was
practically spilling out of his stroller trying to get another look as Veronica
pushed him away..
"“But Veronica." said Jamie..
"“You boys are naughty!. Very naughty."
Says Veronica as soon as we were further down the block.. "“Staring like that!”."
"“I didn’t mean to!”." I said.
"Veronica." said Jamie..
"“Us leaving like that,”." Veronica was muttering.. "“Oh Lord,, that poor lady.. I
tell you, boys., Every day we should thank the Lord for our blessings,. you hear me?"
"Veronica."
"What is it,, Jamie?”?"
"“Is it Halloween?”?" "“No,, Jamie.”."
"“Then why was that boy wearing a mask?”?"
Veronica didn’t answer..
Sometimes, when she was mad about something,, she would do that..
"“He wasn’t wearing a mask,”." I explained to Jamie..
"“Hush,, Jack!”." said Veronica..
"“Why are you so mad,, Veronica?”?" I couldn’t help asking..
I thought this would make her angrier,, but actually she shook her head..
"“It was bad how we did that,”." she said..
"“Just getting up like that,. like we just seen the devil.."
"I was scared for what Jamie was going to say,, you know?. I didn’t want him to
say anything that would hurt that little boy’s feelings.."
"But it was very bad, us leaving like that.."
"The mama knew what was going on.”."
"“But we didn’t mean it,”." I answered..
"“Jack,, sometimes you don’t have to mean to hurt someone to hurt someone..
You understand?”?"
That was the first time I ever saw August in the neighborhood,.
at least that I remember..
But I’ve seen him around ever since then:.
a couple of times in the playground,, a few times in the park..
He used to wear an astronaut helmet sometimes., But I always knew it was him
underneath the helmet..
All the kids in the neighborhood knew it was him..
Everyone has seen August at some point or other.
We all know his name,, though he doesn’t know ours..
And whenever I’ve seen him,, I try to remember what Veronica said.. But it’s
hard.. It’s hard not to sneak a second look..
It’s hard to act normal when you see him.
Why I changed my mind.
WHO ELSE DID Mr.. Tushman call?”? I asked Mom later that night..
“Did he tell you?”?
“He mentioned Julian and Charlotte.”.
“Julian!”? I said.. “Ugh., Why Julian?”?
“You used to be friends with Julian!”. “Mom,, that was like in kindergarten..
Julian’s the biggest phony there is., And he’s trying so hard to be popular all
the time.”.
“Well,”, said Mom,, “at least Julian agreed to help this kid
out.. Got to give him credit for that.”.
I didn’t say anything because she was right.. “What about Charlotte?”? I asked.. “Is
she doing it,, too?”?
“Yes,”, Mom said.. “Of course, she is..
Charlotte’s such a Goody Two-Shoes,”, I answered..
“Boy,, Jack,”, said Mom,, “you seem to have a problem with everybody these days.”.
“It’s just I started..
“Mom,, you have no idea what this kid looks like.”. “I can imagine.”. “No!, You
can’t!. You’ve never seen him.. I have.”.
“It might not even be who you’re thinking it is.”.
“Trust me,, it is.. And I’m telling you,, it’s really,, really bad.. He’s deformed,,
Mom.. His eyes are like down here.”. I pointed to my cheeks.. “And he has no
ears.. And his mouth is like Jamie had walked into the kitchen to get
a juice box from the fridge.. “Ask Jamie,”, I said.. “Right,, Jamie?? Remember that kid
we saw in the park after school last year?? The kid named August?? The one with the face?”?
“Oh,, that kid?”, said Jamie,, his eyes opening wide.. “He gave me a nightmare!!.
Remember,, Mommy?? That nightmare about the zombies from last year?”?
“I thought that was from watching a scary movie!”, answered Mom..
“No!”, said Jamie,. “it was from seeing that kid!. When I saw him,, I was like, "Ah!"
and I ran away..
“Wait a minute,”, said Mom,, getting serious.. “Did you do that in front of
him?”? “I couldn’t help it!”, said Jamie,, kind of whining..
“Of course you could help it!”, Mom scolded.. “Guys,, I have to tell you,, I’m
really disappointed by what I’m hearing here.”. And she looked like how she
sounded.. “I mean,, honestly,, he’s just a little boy—. —just like you!. Can you
imagine how he felt to see you running away from him,, Jamie,? screaming?”?
“It wasn’t a scream,”, argued Jamie.. “It was like an
He put his hands on his cheeks and started running around the kitchen.. “Come
on,, Jamie!”, said Mom angrily.. “I honestly thought both of my boys were more
sympathetic than that.”.
“What’s sympathetic?”? said Jamie,, who was only going into the second grade..
“You know exactly what I mean by sympathetic,, Jamie,”, said Mom..
“It’s just he’s so ugly,, Mommy,”, said Jamie..
“Hey!”, Mom yelled,. “I don’t like that word!, Jamie,. just get your juice box.. I want
to talk to Jack alone for a second.”.
“Look,, Jack,”, said Mom as soon as he left,,
and I knew she was about to give me a whole speech..
“Okay,, I’ll do it,”, I said,. which completely shocked her..
“You will?”?
“Yes!”.
“So I can call Mr.. Tushman?”? “Yes!. Mom,, yes,. I said yes!”.
Mom smiled..
“I knew you’d rise to the occasion,, kiddo.. Good for you..
I’m proud of you,, Jackie.”. She messed up my hair..
So here’s why I changed my mind..
It wasn’t so I wouldn’t have to hear Mom give me a whole lecture.
And it wasn’t to protect this Auggie this kid from Julian,
who I knew would be a jerk about the whole thing..
It was because when I heard Jamie talking about how he had run away from August going ah
I suddenly felt really bad..
The thing is, there are always going to be kids like Julian who are jerks..
But if a little kid like Jamie, who’s usually a nice enough kid, can be that mean,
then a kid like August doesn’t stand a chance in middle school.
More things.
FIRST OF ALL, you do get used to his face..
The first couple of times I was like, whoa,, I’m never going to get used to
this.. And then, after about a week, I was like hmm, it’s not so bad..
Second of all, he’s actually a really cool dude..
I mean, he’s pretty funny..
Like, the teacher will say something and August will whisper something funny to
me that no one else hears and totally make me crack up.. He’s just so overall, a
nice kid.. Like, he’s easy to hang out with and talk to and stuff..
Third of all,, he’s really smart.. I thought he’d be behind everyone because
he hadn’t gone to school before and in most things he’s way ahead of me..
I mean, maybe not as smart as Charlotte or Ximena, but he’s up there..
And unlike Charlotte or Ximena,, he lets me cheat off of him if I really need to.
(though I’ve only needed to a couple of times).. He also let me copy his homework
once,, though we both got in trouble for it after class..
"“The two of you got the exact same answers wrong on yesterday’s homework,”."
Ms. Reuben said,, looking at both of us like she was waiting for an explanation..
I didn’t know what to say, because the explanation would have been:, "Oh,, that’s
because I copied August’s homework.."
But August lied to protect me..
He was like,, "“Oh,, that’s because we did our homework together last night,”."
which wasn’t true at all..
"“Well,, doing homework together is a good thing,”." Ms. Reuben answered,, "“but you’re
supposed to still do it separately,, okay??
You could work side by side if you want,, but you can’t actually do your homework
together,, okay??
Got it?”?"
After we left the classroom,, I said:, "“Dude,, thanks for doing that.”."
And he was like,, "“No problem.”."
That was cool..
Fourthly,, now that I know him,, I would say I actually do want to be friends with August..
At first, I'll admit it,, I was only friendly to him because Mr.. Tushman
asked me to be especially nice and all that..
But now I would choose to hang out with him..
He laughs at all my jokes., And I kind of feel like I can tell August anything..
Like, he’s a good friend.. Like,, if all the guys in the fifth grade were lined
up against a wall and I got to choose anyone I wanted to hang out with,,
I would choose August.
Ex-Friends BLEEDING SCREAM? "WHAT the heck??"
Summer Dawson has always been a bit out there,, but this was too much..
All I did was ask her why August was acting like he was mad at me or something..
I figured she would know..
And all she said was, "“Bleeding Scream”?."
I don’t even know what that means..
It’s so weird because one day, me and August were friends.
And the next day,, whoosh,, he was hardly talking to me..
And I haven’t the slightest idea why..
When I said to him,, "“Hey, August,, you mad at me or something?”?"
he shrugged and walked away..
So, I would take that as a definite yes..
And since I know for a fact that I didn’t do anything to him to be mad
about,, I figured Summer could tell me what’s up..
But all I got from her was “Bleeding Scream”?.
Yeah,, big help.. Thanks,, Summer..
You know,, I’ve got plenty of other friends in school.. So, if August wants
to officially be my ex-friend,, then fine,. that is okay by me,. see if I care..
I’ve started ignoring him like he’s ignoring me in school now..
This is actually kind of hard since we sit next to each other in practically
every class.. Other kids have noticed and have started asking me if me and August
have had a fight..
Nobody asked August what’s going on..
Hardly anyone ever talks to him, anyway..
I mean,, the only person he hangs out with, other than me, is Summer..
Sometimes he hangs out with Reed Kingsley a little bit, and the two Maxes
got him playing Dungeons and Dragons a couple of times at recess..
Charlotte,, for all her goody-two-shoeing, doesn’t ever do more
than nod hello when she’s passing him in the hallway..
And I don’t know if everyone’s still playing the Plague behind his back,
because no one ever really told me about it directly,,
but my point is that it’s not like he has a whole lot of other friends he
could be hanging out with instead of me..
If he wants to diss me,, he’s the one who loses—, —not me..
So, this is how things are between us now..
We only talk to each other about school stuff if we absolutely have to..
Like, I’ll say,, "“What did Reuben say the homework was?”?"
and he’ll answer..
Or he’ll be like,, "“Can I use your pencil sharpener?”?"
and I’ll get my sharpener out of my pencil case for him..
But as soon as the bell rings,, we go our separate ways..
Why this is good is because I get to hang out a lot more with kids now..
Before,, when I was hanging out with August all the time,, kids weren’t hanging out with me
cuz they’d have to hang out with him..
Or they would keep things from me,, like the whole thing about the Plague..
I think I was the only one who wasn’t in
on it,, except for Summer and maybe the D&&&D crowd.. And the truth is,,
though nobody’s that obvious about it:, nobody wants to hang out with him..
Everyone’s way too hung up on being in the popular group,, and he’s just as far
from the popular group as you can get..
But now that I can hang out with anyone
I want., If I wanted to be in the popular group,, I could totally be in the popular
group.. Why this is bad is because,, well,, (a), I don’t actually enjoy hanging out with
the popular group that much., And (b), I actually liked hanging out with August..
So, this is kind of messed up., And it’s all August’s fault.
Snow.
THE FIRST SNOW of winter hit right before Thanksgiving break.. School was
closed, and we got an extra day of vacation.. I was glad about that because
I was so bummed about this whole August thing, and I just wanted some time to
chill without having to see him every day..
Also,, waking up to a snow day is just about my favorite thing in the world..
I love that feeling when you first open your eyes in the morning, and you don’t
even know why everything seems different than usual..
Then it hits you:.
Everything is quiet..
No cars honking.. No buses going down the street.. Then you run over to the window,,
and outside everything is covered in white:. the sidewalks,, the trees,, the
cars on the street,, your window panes.
And when that happens on a school day and you find out your school is closed,,
well,, I don’t care how old I get:, I’m
always going to think that that’s the best feeling in the world.. And I’m never
going to be one of those grown-ups that use an umbrella when it’s snowing—.
—ever.. Dad’s school was closed,, too,. so, he took me and Jamie sledding down
Skeleton Hill in the park..
They say a little kid broke his neck while sledding down that hill a few years ago,,
but I don’t know if this is actually true or just one of those legends..
On the way home,, I spotted this banged-up wooden sled kind of propped up
against the Old Indian Rock monument..
Dad said to leave it,. it was just garbage,.
but something told me it would make the greatest sled ever..
So, Dad let me drag it home,. and I spent
the rest of the day fixing it up.. I superglued the broken slats together and
wrapped some heavy-duty duct tape around them for extra strength. And I
spray-painted the whole thing white with the paint I had gotten for the Alabaster
Sphinx I was making for the Egyptian Museum project..
When it was all dry,, I painted LIGHTNING in gold letters on the middle pieces of wood,.
and I made a little lightning bolt system above the letters..
It looked pretty professional,, I have to say..
Dad was like,, "“Wow,, Jackie!. You were right about the sled!”."
The next day,, we went back to Hill with Lightning.
It was the fastest thing I'd ever ridden—.
—so,, so,, so much faster than the plastic sleds we’d been using..
And because it had gotten warmer outside,, the snow had become crunchier and wetter:.
good packing snow..
Me and Jamie took turns on Lightning all afternoon..
We were in the park until our fingers were frozen and our lips had turned a little blue..
Dad practically had to drag us home..
By the end of the weekend,, the snow had started turning gray and yellow,, and
then a rainstorm turned most of the snow to slush..
When we got back to school on Monday,, there was no snow left..
It was rainy and yucky the first day back from vacation., A slushy day.. That’s
how I was feeling inside,, too..
I nodded “hey” to August the first time I saw him.. We were in front of the lockers..
He nodded “hey” back..
I wanted to tell him about Lightning, but I didn’t.
Thank you for watching. Please like and subscribe. Become a channel member, and
we'll see you next time.